Guide to the Murrysville Garden Club Records, 1952-2016 AIS.2016.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Murrysville Garden Club Records
1952-2016
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Murrysville Garden Club
AIS.2016.05
6 Linear Feet (9 records center boxes, 2 document cases, and 1 oversized folder)
This collection documents the function and activities of the Murrysville Garden Club (MGC) from 1952 to 2016. Included are organization yearbooks, meeting minutes, financial and committee reports, newsletters, awards, project records, clippings related to the MGC, the records of the Murrysville Junior Garden Club Earth Team, correspondence, photographs, and audio-visual materials.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Murrysville Garden Club on September 8, 2016.
Arrangement
This collection consists of 12 series.
Series I. Yearbooks
Series II. Minutes
Series III. Financial Records
Series IV. Reports
Series V. Newsletters
Series VI. Awards & Scholarships
Series VII. Events & Projects
Series VIII. Clippings
Series IX. Junior Garden Club Earth Team
Series X. Correspondence
Series XI. Photographs
Series XII. Audio-Visual Materials
Biography/History
The Murrysville Garden Club (MGC) was founded on March 26, 1952 by Anna Cotter. Cotter, a 1951 Pennsylvania State University graduate with a degree in Agriculture, served as the MGC's inaugural president from 1952-1953. The MGC Creed, which first appeared in the organization's 1953 yearbook, describes the Club's purpose as being twofold. First, it stated that the Club existed to promote the idea that humanity had an obligation to preserve nature. Second, it expressed the belief that gardening could enrich members' lives through its unique social, environmental, and personal experiences. In its first year, the MGC totaled sixty-three members. By 1960, this number had expanded to ninety-nine. Since 1975, membership has ranged between fifty and a hundred members, averaging around between sixty and seventy members annually.
The MGC's commitment to particpating in events in Murrysville locally and Westmoreland County regionally expanded between 1970 and 1990. The MGC had had a youth outreach program through the late 1950s and 1960s, but this endeavor was much less central to the MGC's overall mission than the one that was born when the organization increased youth activites in the 1970s and 1980s. It was during this time that the MGC Junior Garden Earth Science Club (called the MGC Junior Garden Club Earth Team after 1999) was founded to teach children the values of the environmental movement.
The 1980s through the 2000s saw a large expansion in the MGC's participation in regional and state garden club competitions. In this period, the MGC began applying for (and winning) a large number of awards from the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania (GCFP), National Council of State Garden Clubs (NCSGC), and National Garden Clubs Incorporated (NGC). The MGC was and remains very active in its membership of the GCFP especially.
Annually, the MGC organizes a sizeable number of community events, including annual garden tours, "May Mart" sales to raise money, Christmas wreath making sessions and holiday sales to raise money but also to make affordable Christmas decorations for the community, and Arbor Day and Earth Day celebrations to promote environmentalism. The MGC organizes "garden therapy" sessions at local nursing homes designed to engage older members of the community, educate citizens about gardening, and promote the therapeutic effects of gardening espoused in the MGC Creed. Frequently, these events are attended by children and members of the MGC Junior Garden Club with the intention of promoting civic awareness. Community projects the MGC has organized include a Route 22 beautification effort to clean up the local roadway and maintenance work at the local federal post office and war memorials.
As part of its mission to promote environmental awareness, the MGC awards college scholarships to those studying fields related to gardening - such as biology, agronomy, and landscaping - and the Business Beautification Award to Murrysville businesses that take steps to maintain their properties in appealing and civically responsible ways.
The MGC is a member of several larger regional and national organizations. As of 2017, these include the National Garden Clubs Incorporated (NGC); the National Council of State Garden Clubs (NCSGC); the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania, District VII (GCFP); the Audubon Society of Western Pennsylvania; the Westmoreland Conservancy; and the Pennsylvania Cleanways organization. Additionally, the MGC has historically tried to keep in contact with the Greensburg Garden Club, another Westmoreland County organization.
Related Material
Garden Club of Allegheny County Records, 1913-2012, AIS.2006.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Fox Chapel Garden Club Records, AIS.2011.10, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pucketos Garden Club Records, AIS.2014.02, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
The Murrysville Garden Club Records are composed of a wide variety of record types, including club minutes, official awards given to and distributed by the MGC, bank and financial statements, photographs, scrapbooks, project files, and ephemera. The MGC is a member of the GCFP (District VII), NCSGC, and NGC. These affiliations compose a significant part of the MGC's history and are well-documented in the collection.
Environmental quality -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County; Photographs; Minutes (Administrative records); Financial records; Correspondence; Gardening -- Pennsylvania -- Murrysville -- Societies, etc.; Gardening -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County -- Societies, etc.; Environmental quality -- Pennsylvania -- Murrysville; Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania; Murrysville Junior Garden Club; Murrysville Garden Club
- Yearbooks, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series consists of the annual yearbooks of the MGC from 1952, the year of its founding, to 2014. The yearbooks of the MGC typically list current club officers, awards won in the past year, past presidents, a membership directory, the Club Creed, a theme for the year, and an overview of ongoing projects. The yearbooks frequently list national and regional affiliations to organizations like the GCFP and NCSGC. Not present in collection are the yearbooks from 1954-1955, 1957, 1964, 1965, 1980, 2009, and 2012-2013. The folders are organized chronologically.
  - Yearbooks, 1952-1959 (Box 1a, Folder 1-4)
  - Yearbooks, 1960-1969 (Box 1a, Folder 5-9)
  - Yearbooks, 1970-1979 (Box 1a, Folder 10-14)
  - Yearbooks, 1980-1990 (Box 1a, Folder 15-20)
  - Yearbooks, 1991-2000 (Box 1a, Folder 21-25)
  - Yearbooks, 2001-2014 (Box 1a, Folder 26-31)
- Minutes, II.
  This series is composed of the proceedings of the meetings of the MGC Executive Board, MGC General Membership, and GCFP Annual Convention. The material in this collection dates from 1963 to 2011. This series is broken into four subseries.
  - Executive Board and General Membership Meeting Combined, 1.
    This subseries is composed of the annual proceedings of the MGC Executive Board and General Membership. These records have been sorted separately from subseries two and three because in these, unlike the documents which compose those series, the authors deliberately preserved the minutes of the Executive Board and General Membership meetings together. In many cases, Executive Board and General Membership meeting records appear on the same page or have been pasted and/or stapled together. This material dates from 1963 to 1989. The years 1970-1979 and 1981-1984 are not included. The folders are organized chronologically. In cases where there is overlap in years covered with other folders, folders have been sorted by the first year mentioned.
    - Minutes, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
    - Minutes, 1980 (Box 1b, Folder 32)
    - Minutes, 1985-1989 (Box 1b, Folder 33)
  - Executive Board, 2.
    This subseries records the proceedings of the meetings of the Executive Board of the MGC. The Executive Board traditionally meets at least once a month, but sometimes meets twice if there is need. Additionally, the Board typically meets for more months out of the year than the General Membership does, meeting during the winter months of the year to plan while the rest of the membership takes time off. The minutes of the Executive Board are composed by the Recording Secretary. This material ranges from 1970 to 2010, with the years 1985 and 1986 not included. The folders are organized chronologically.
    - Minutes, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34-40)
    - Minutes, 1987-2010 (Box 1, Folder 41-51)
    - Minutes, 2001-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - General Membership Meeting, 3.
    This series consists of the proceedings of the General Membership meetings of the MGC. While there has historically been some variation, General Membership meetings are typically held once a month from January or February through November. General Membership meetings are open to the entirety of the Club body and typically consist of officers making reports in turn. As with Executive Board minutes, those of the General Membership meeting are composed by the Recording Secretary. The material ranges from 1970 to 2010, with the years 1984-1988 not included. The folders are organized chronologically.
    - Minutes, 1970-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11-16)
    - Minutes, 1989-2010 (Box 2, Folder 17-36)
  - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Annual Convention, 4.
    This subseries is composed of the minutes of the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania's (GCFP) annual meetings. The yearly meeting brings together delegates from regional member organizations such as the Murrsyville Garden Club. The GCFP Annual Convention recognizes the accomplishments of individual clubs and their members, considers motions changing the rules of the organization, and offers a variety of activities related to gardening and Pennsylvania heritage for delegates. The minutes of the GCFP Annual Convention are publicly published. The material in this subseries ranges from 2006-2011, with the years 2009-2010 not included. The folders are organized chronologically.
    - Meeting Minutes, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Financial Records, III.
  This series is composed of the financial records of the MGC, including revenue and expense reports, budgets and proposed budgets, and official bank statements. The material dates from 1962-2012. The folders are organized alphabetically.
  - Budget of the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Financial and Bank Statements, 1999-2012 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Property Holdings, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Proposed Budgets, 1962-2009 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Revenue and Expense Summaries, 1988-2004 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Reports, IV.
  This series consists of the reports of committees and committee chairmen to the MGC president. Reports are typically collected annually and summarize actions taken in the previous year. The material dates from 1954-2013. The folders are organized aphabetically first and then chronologically.
  - Annual Reports, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Annual Reports, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Arbor Day Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Arbor Day Committee Annual Reports, 1993-2007 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Arbor Day Committee Annual Reports, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Auditing Committee Annual Reports, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Awards Committee Annual Reports, 1971-2013 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Birds Chairman Annual Report, Undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Business Beautification Committee Annual Reports, 1993-2012 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - By-Laws, 1993-2010 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Christmas Workshop Annual Reports, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Civic and Conservation Committee Annual Reports, 1984-2012 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Communities Incorporated Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Community Day Annual Reports, 2001; 2004 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Community Gardening Committee Annual Report, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Corresponding Secretary Annual Reports, 1990-2012 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - District VII Meeting Reports, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Environmental Concerns Commitee Annual Reports, 2005-2012 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Evening Auxiliary Committee Formation Proposal, Undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Field Trip Committee Annual Reports, 1996-2011 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Finance Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Finance Committee Annual Reports, 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Flower Show Chairman Annual Reports, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Flower Show Chairman Annual Reports, 2001-2011 (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
  - Garden Therapy Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2012 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Garden Tour Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Garden Tour Committee Annual Reports, 1994-2012 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Greensburg Garden Club Representative Job Description, Undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Greensburg Garden Club Representative Annual Reports, 2004-2011 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Historian Annual Report, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Horticulture Committee Annual Reports, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Horticulture Committee Annual Reports, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Horticulture Committee Annual Reports, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Horticulture Committee Annual Reports, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Hospitality Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2012 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Hostess Committee Annual Reports, 1997-2009 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Librarian Annual Reports, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - May Mart Committee Annual Reports, 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Membership Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Membership Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2008 (Box 2, Folder 86-89)
  - Membership Committee Annual Reports, 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - National Council of State Garden Clubs Guide for New Officers and Committees, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Needs and Concerns Committee Annual Reports, 1998-2012 (Box 2, Folder 92-93)
  - Nominating Committee Annual Reports, 1992-2009 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Photography Special Committee Annual Reports, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Plant Sale Annual Reports, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plant Sale Annual Reports, 2000-2013 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
  - President's Annual Reports, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - President's Annual Report, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - President's Luncheon Committee Annual Reports, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Program Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Program Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2006 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publicity Chairman Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Publicity Chairman Annual Reports, 1979-2011 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
  - Recipe Book Chairman Report, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Recording Secretary Job Description, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Recording Secretary Annual Reports, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Route 22 Beautification Chairman Annual Reports, 2006-2012 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Scholarship Chairman Job Description, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scholarship Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2012 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Student Award Chairman Annual Reports, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Telephone and Transportation Committee Chairman Job Description, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Telephone and Transportation Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2002 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Treasurer and Assistant Treasurer Job Descriptions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Treasurer's Annual Reports, 1979-1998 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Treasurer's Annual Reports, 2000-2013 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ways and Means Committee Job Description, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Ways and Means Committee Annual Reports, 1990-2008 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Yearbook Committee Annual Reports, 1998-2012 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Newsletters, V.
  This series consists of the newsletters of the MGC. Club newsletters are compiled monthly and mailed to members. Newsletters are not published publicly and serve as internal updates of the Club's activity. The newsletters are typically produced from February or March through November and consist of a letter from the Club president, a schedule, a concerns and well-wishes section, a recipe-of-the-month, and any pertinent committee or project updates that concern the entire membership. The material dates from 1970-2013, with the years 1979, 1980-1981, 1983, and 2012 not included. The folders are organized chronologically.
  - Newsletters, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Newsletters, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 32-38)
  - Newsletters, 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 39-48)
- Awards & Scholarships, VI.
  This series includes all awards, honors, certificates, and citations given to the MGC. The series also includes all awards and scholarships given by the Club to other parties. It is broken into two subseries. The material dates from 1972-2014.
  - Awards Recieved, 1.
    This series is composed of all awards and forms of recognition that have been given to the MGC. The vast majority of these records are awards given to the Club by the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania (GCFP), National Council of State Garden Clubs (NCSGC), and National Garden Clubs Incorporated (NGC). The material is composed of scrapbooks, award applications, offical awards, and ephemera, such as wooden plaques and ribbons. Also included is oversized signage related to awards in the subseries. The material dates from 1975-2012. The folders are organized alphabetically and then chronologically.
    - Awards Won Summaries, 1994-2005 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Beverly Healthcare Recognition Plaque, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - CARE Certificate of Appreciation, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Franklin Regional School District Excellence Award, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Annual Convention Lists of Award Recipients, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Blue Rosette Award, 1984-2002 (Box 3, Folder 67-72)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Certificate of Appreciation, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Civic Achievement Award, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Civic Concern Award, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Civic Concern Award, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Civic Development or Improvement Award, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Club Program Award, 1985-1996 (Box 3, Folder 78-84)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Fifty Year Club Certificate, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Flower Show Schedule Award, 1975-2006 (Box 3, Folder 86-91)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Flower Show Staged in a Public Building Award, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Gardening Among Youth Award, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Gardening Among Youth Award, 2005-2009 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Governor's Trophy, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 95-97)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Governor's Trophy, 1988-2006 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Holiday Achievement Award, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Honor Roll for Exceptional Achievement, 1981-2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Horticulture Achievement Award, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Horticulture Excellence Award, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Horticulture Therapy Award, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Laurel and Daffodil Awards, 1979-2012 (Box 4, Folder 17-35)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Myrrel R. Overdorff Community Action Award, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Newsletter Award, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Outstanding Achievement Award, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Outstanding Achievement Award, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Penny Pines Award, 2007-2011 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Publication Award, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Publication Award, 1989-2003 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Publicity Press Book Award, 1981-2002 (Box 5, Folder 11-20)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Seed Money Grant Award, 2005-2008 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Silver Award, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Special Achievement Certificate, 1992-1998 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Special Recognition Award, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Special Recognition State Award, 1995-2008 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Specialized Publication Award, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Staging Award, 1981-1995 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Standard Flower Show, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Standard Flower Show Schedule Award, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Superior Flower Show Award, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Yearbook Award, 1975-2011 (Box 5, Folder 31-36)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania Video Club Program Award, 1992-1997 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania and National Garden Clubs Incorporated Flower Show Award Ribbons, Undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Greensburg Garden Center Volunteer Appreciation Award, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Municipality of Murrysville Mayoral Proclamation, Undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Municipality of Murrysville Meritorious Citation, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Murray Manor Convalescent Center Very Important Person and Volunteer Awards, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Award of Honor, 1994-2002 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Burgundy and Pink Rosette, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Dean World Gardening Trophy, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Flower Show Achievement Award, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Garden Therapy Certificate of Merit, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Lucile Droege Mauntel Conservation Award, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Lucile Droege Mauntel Conservation Award, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs Member Award for Conservation, Undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs National Flower Show Achievement Award, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs National Flower Show Achievement Award, 1997 (Box 6a, Folder 1)
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs National Flower Show Achievement Award, 1999 (Box 6a, Folder 2)